Finding Aid for The Rufus Wilmot Griswold Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Rufus Wilmot Griswold Collection
1812-1857
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0183
.42 linear_feet
Biographical Sketch
Rufus Wilmot Griswold was born February 13, 1815 in Benson, Vermont. He was an editor and literary critic best known for his anthologies of American poetry and prose which were widely disseminated in the mid 19th century and for his often tumultuous and contentious relationships, both personal and literary.
He had a strained relationship with Edgar Allan Poe that continued even after Poe’s death, with an obituary written under the pen name of “Ludwig” that was highly derogatory towards the deceased. Griswold subsequently became Poe’s literary executor under mysterious circumstances and continued to defame Poe in a written “Memoir of the Author,” included in a posthumous collection of his works, that combined false accusations with character assassination that was not refuted for many years and became the standard Poe biography.
He was married three times, had three children and, after a period of declining health, passed away in New York on August 27, 1857.
Scope and Content Note
The Rufus Wilmot Griswold Collection (1815 – 1857) consists of one Hollinger box (0.417 linear feet) and includes holograph letters, photographs, articles and photostats of letters written by and to Rufus Wilmot Griswold.
The collection was formed in the 1930’s by Joy Bayless of Nashville, Tennessee while researching her biography of Rufus Wilmot Griswold which was published by Vanderbilt University Press in 1943. No records have survived as to when or how the Collection was acquired by the Vanderbilt Library.
- Catalogue of The Rufus W. Griswold Collection of Manuscripts in the Boston Public Library. 114 p., typed carbon. (Folder 1)
- 2 original holograph letters by Griswold, 1 dated January 1855, to Jos. T. Fields, Esq., the other dated Monday, to Dr. Somer. (Folder 2)
- Pictures of Griswold and his first wife. 1 engraving of Griswold, 1 photograph of an engraving of Griswold, 2 photographs of paintings of Griswold, 1 photograph of a painting of Mrs. Griswold. (Folder 3)
- Offprint articles: “Another Rufus W. Griswold as a Critic of Poe,” by Joy Bayless; “The Letters of Edgar A. Poe to George W. Eveleth,” ed. by James Southall Wilson. (Folder 4)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, February 1939, about Poe. (Folder 5)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to Griswold, 1842-56 (Folder 6)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to Griswold, 1842-56 (Folder 7)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to Griswold, 1842-55 (Folder 8)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to Griswold, 1848-56 (Folder 9)
- Photostats from Boston Public library, letters to Griswold, 1834, 1854 (Folder 10)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to and from Griswold, 1848-56 (Folder 11)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to Griswold, 1850-56 (Folder 12)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to Griswold, 1840, 1853 (Folder 13)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters from and poems by Mrs. Sarah Helen Whitman, 1838, 1847 (Folder 14)
- Photostats from Boston Public Library, letters to and from Griswold, 1843, 1847 (Folder 15)
- Photostats from Connecticut State Historical Society, letters from Horace Greeley and Mrs. Sigourney to Mrs. Stephens, 1842, 1843 (Folder 16)
- Photostats from Cornell University Library, letters from Griswold to B. Taylor, 1843, 1846 (Folder 17)
- Photostats from Harvard College Library, letters from Griswold, 1842, 1849 (Folder 18)
- Photostats from Historical Society of Pennsylvania, letters to and from Griswold, 1842-1856 (Folder 19)
- Photostats from Historical Society of Pennsylvania, letters to George R. Graham, Esq., 1841-1845 (Folder 20)
- Photostats from Huntington Library, letters from Griswold, 1853 (Folder 21)
- Photostats from Huntington Library, letters to James Fields from Griswold, [n.d.] (Folder 22)
- Photostats from Huntington Library, letters to James Fields from Griswold, 1841-1845 (Folder 23)
- Photostat from Library Company, letters from Griswold to J. Smith, 1854 (Folder 24)
- Photostats from New York Historical Society, letters to and from Griswold, 1847-1854 (Folder 25)
- Photostats from New York Public Library, letters from Griswold, 1839-1844 (Folder 26)
- Photostats from New York Public Library, letters from Griswold, 1847-1856 (Folder 27)
- Photostat from Widener Library, Griswold to Longfellow, 1847 (Folder 28)
- Photostats from Yale University Library, letters from Griswold, 1841-1854 (Folder 29)
- Typed and handwritten copies of letters from various collections: Poe Foundation, Lilly Collection, American Antiquarian Society, Pierpont Morgan Library. Also 1 unidentified photostat of poem. (Folder 30)
- Typed and handwritten copies of letters owned by Gerrit Griswold of Batavia. (Folder 31)
- Typed copies of two Nathaniel Hawthorne letters, from Huntington Library and Historical Society of Pennsylvania. (Folder 32)